- Hello . I 'm Park Chan-wook . - And I 'm Lee Dong-jin .
We will start the commentary on the film The Housemaid .
Yes .
I really didn 't know that this film was going to be released on Blu-ray Disc .
This is an important event in film history .
The Housemaid is an exceptional film that occupies
an important and special place in Korea film history .
So I believe this commentary will be very important to many Korean film lovers .
I don 't watch same movies again and again ,
even the ones I like . I watched this movie only
once a long time ago , and watched it again to prepare for the commentary .
- So I 've watched it only twice . - I see .
I was worried that I might be disappointed with the movie .
But I was shocked when I watched it .
You saw it again this morning before we started recording the commentary .
I did .
The director Kim Ki-young made several great films , but
I wondered again how he was able to create this cinematic masterpiece .
And even among his great films , I realized again that
this film is really special .
The whole film is shot like the one in a picture frame .
Now the prologue part of the film is over .
And they are playing the game of cat 's cradle .
I think this is a great backdrop for credits .
Yes .
It 's great because the scene is simple and repetitive ,
but I am curious why the director wanted to use it here .
Later , the film shows a cotton mill , so he may want to connect it
to making thread and weaving .
Yes , I think so .
But the wife in this house uses a sewing machine all the time ,
and the film brings up the image of thread , cloth , and clothes .
- Which repeats . - Yes , it keeps repeating .
Cat 's cradle is not an easy game to play because if you make
one wrong move , the thread becomes undone .
So he is bringing that ...
That sense of tension .
We can guess that this game symbolizes risk ,
or things that can come undone .
Also , building a house is important in this film .
Especially building a two-story house .
- It represents a desire of the middle class . - That 's true .
It is a visual representation of that desire .
And the game of cat 's cradle is like building a house .
- It is architectural in a way . - Yes .
The game can be difficult to play , but the patterns
repeat themselves .
So the game keeps going in circles .
It 's not used as a metaphor , but it as a literal manifestation of that idea .
- Things going in circles is an image in the film . - Yes .
Here , she is spinning the sewing machine .
And they are spinning machines at the cotton mill .
Like fate that keeps going in circles without an exit .
Those are the ideas that I associated with the first image .
The maid , played by Lee Eun-sim ,
just passed by in the scene .
I didn 't know she showed up so early in the film .
When I watched the film for the first time , I didn 't see her , but
watching it the second time , I realized she works at the mill .
But she doesn 't show her face .
I 'm guessing that she works at the cafeteria in the factory ,
although it might not be the cafeteria .
- She looks like a cleaning woman . - She does .
So she is a character who does odd jobs at the mill .
The fact she is a cleaning woman means
- that even at the mill ... - Yes .
Even in this textile factory ,
people are divided into different classes .
I didn 't know that was her because I couldn 't see her face , but
she wears the same clothes when she moves into Dong-sik 's house .
I see .
And there is a close-up scene with the mop , which seems unnecessary ,
and the scene is repeated as if for emphasis .
It 's obvious that the scene is in the film for a reason .
Yes .
And Kim Jin-kyu plays Dong-sik .
I searched for information about Kim Jin-kyu , and I found out that
he was 38 when he filmed this movie .
- But ... - He looks older .
A Korean actor who is 38 now is
Won Bin .
Kim Jin-kyu was the same age as Won Bin when he filmed this .
It 's hard to believe .
After playing Dong-sik in this film ,
he was in Aimless Bullet the following year .
The two films have always been rated as
the top two films in Korean film history by film critics .
- Right . - The two films have competed for first place .
And he was in the top two films one after the other .
He was .
He was a great actor , and those were the best years that he had as an actor .
He was well known for the image of a gentleman and an intellect ,
but he wasn 't so highly educated in reality .
But in films , he often played intellectual characters ,
- or incompetent fathers . - He did
In some ways , the character that he plays in this film overlaps
- with the character he plays in Aimless Bullet . - That 's true .
But in The Road to Sampo , he plays a very different character .
This is the scene in which he finds a love letter .
But he reports it to the superintendent . He is a tattletale .
I thought this was a really unexpected and interesting way to start the story .
Dong-sik is a character with castration anxiety , and this loss of masculinity
is manifested in his fear of losing his job .
And telling the superintendent about the letter comes from that fear .
Yes .
He 's afraid of the love letter growing into a scandal ,
and that it would eventually cost him his livelihood .
- There is definitely that . - And at the same time ,
he pretends to be a very ethical person when , in fact ,
- he is very repressed . - That 's true .
He could have just dismissed it .
And even the superintendent expresses her concern that
it might cause harm to the mill worker who wrote the letter .
And she asks whether he has to go to that extreme .
But he does something that makes him look like a prick
or some kind of puritan
who expects even other people to be morally impeccable .
But the way he behaves later on shows him to be the very opposite .
There is the maid again .
I see .
I was paying attention only to the stairs .
The stairs in this film symbolize one of its important thematic ideas .
- It 's a spatial image . - Yes
So the film gives viewers a sneak preview of what is to come even here in the mill scene .
Director Kim Ki-young was called eccentric or idiosyncratic ,
or a director with a taste for the grotesque ,
or a show-off who likes to flaunt his style .
He was often described that way ,
but when you watch his films , you realize they were made
based on meticulous calculations , which seem almost mathematical .
That is especially true in this film .
It is so true regarding the plot of the film as well as the cutting of the scenes .
For example , Director Ha Gil-jong once said that Kim Ki-young
was the Korean director who was most exact with scene cutting .
Director Ha said this some time in the 70s .
Director Kim had a near perfect sense when it came to
the camera angle or the size of the scene .
He was famous for that in Chungmu-ro .
- When I was just starting out in the industry , - Yes ?
I used to ask everyone who had been in the field for a while
whether they ever had a chance to work with Director Kim .
Those who did unanimously said that he was a perfectionist ,
and that he was always precise about where cameras should be .
He told the cameramen where their cameras should be
and gave them specific instructions on the size of the camera lens ,
- whether 35 mm or 50 mm . - He did ... I see .
And when they looked in their cameras , actors were exactly where they should be .
So like Hitchcock , Director Kim started making films after
he had learned everything there was to learn about cameras and camera lenses .
In the film , the set designs also play an important role .
People said that the director himself hammered nails in
in the sets for this film .
And the editing ... the way he edited the film
is just amazing , even from today 's point of view .
His editing choices were bold , and the story never drags even for a moment .
The story takes place inside one house , and with so much repetition , but
- there is not one moment of dullness . - Not one !
Nothing drags on .
And there are a lot of movements with cameras .
And he also used cranes a lot .
Now we are looking at the house before the family moves into it .
They are not well-off , and you see the piano and the sewing machine
together in one place . Like in his other movies , in which you find
conflicting character images or things that represent contradicting ideas ,
in The Housemaid , you see the piano and the sewing machine ,
which represent two different images .
If I were to have a different title for the film , it would be
The Piano and The Sewing Machine .
- Not only those two things ... - Yes ?
The film uses different pieces of furniture or one specific body part
over and over again , and it explores all possible interpretations of the images
by showing them in different contexts .
In the beginning of the film , everyone in the family is excited
about moving into their new house because
it means they are moving up , especially on the social ladder .
But their girl had polio , which left her lame .
The fact that she is lame brings a certain mood
into the film from the beginning .
- That is true . - The image of the family ,
which seems perfect on the surface is offset
by their girl who is lame .
And the father is almost cruel to his own daughter .
Her younger brother , played by Ahn Sung-ki , treats her the same way .
She is treated with the same coldness and even meanness by her father
and brother . She is like the dirty laundry that the family wants to hide .
And this might sound very cruel but to her family , she is like a dirty stain .
They seem to think that their family would be
really perfect if only she wasn 't lame .
Everyone in the family seems to think that .
Ahn Sung-ki was 11 at the time .
He was in another film by Kim Ki-young , called The Twilight Train
- two years prior to being in this one . - I see .
Ms. Kim Ji-mi also made her debut in The Twilight Train .
- There is the maid again . - Yes , that 's her .
- Now I can tell just by looking at her back . - And her clothes , too .
- She has her hair braided . - She does .
This is really a strange scene .
This is where female mill workers change their clothes .
But Dong-sik just marches in I don 't know what he thinks he is doing .
One of the recurring themes in this film seems to be about
- intrusion . - Right .
It can be a physical intrusion , or
- intrusions that are visual or auditory in nature . - I see .
The film seems to be making a declaration that it is about intrusions .
- Yes ... - So it has a character that marches into a place like that .
What stands out in this scene is that
a man walks into a factory of all female workers .
What happens later is that the maid ...
- Yes . - The maid walks into the house
- like some kind of virus . - Yes .
Which actually reminded me of your film , Thirst .
What really surprised me when I was watching the movie early this morning
was how it had sub - consciously influenced me .
I saw things that came across as being awfully familiar .
It was a really long time ago when I saw this film for the first time .
- And I forgot about it . - Yes ?
I am notorious for being forgetful , so
I thought I didn 't remember any of this film , but
it must have stayed somewhere in me , and without my being aware of it ,
it must have influenced me when I made my movies ,
like Thirst or Sympathy for Mr. Vengeance .
In Thirst , The Happy Hanbok Place is also a two-story ,
- A two story building . - Right .
- And I have a character who wears traditional clothes . - Right .
And the clothes give viewers a similar feel as it does in this film .
Dong-sik 's wife always wears a traditional dress .
And Ms. Um Aing-ran was just rising to stardom at the time .
Yes , that was the case .
By the time she made this film , it had been four years since she had debuted as an actress .
And this movie came out before her hit film , The Barefooted Young .
That 's right .
She is the most fashionable character in the film .
And it 's obvious she paid a lot of attention to what she wore in the film .
She was famous for her slender waist .
And she wears dresses that draw attention to her waist .
But what is unexpected is that
she does not change into that many different dresses .
In the beginning of the film , she wears the same dress ,
and she doesn 't change into a different dress for a long time .
You 're right .
I thought about why , and I realized this film
simplifies and repeats images based on meticulous calculation .
You mean to create a sense of rhythm in the film .
Reading the reviews from the time when the film was released ,
critics pointed out that the camera angle in the choir scenes
was too simple , and it is true ,
since the scenes were filmed using the same exact camera angle
again and again . The street scenes in front of the house were also
shot from the same camera angle .
So the film is able to draw more attention to the changes
that take place by repeatedly presenting viewers with the same scenes
again and again . After that , the film slowly makes its way
to destroying what it has built up through the repetition .
Yes , the situation slowly gets worse as time passes .
The scene in which Dong-sik is giving Gyeong-hui a piano lesson
clearly shows the sexual tension between the two ,
with their hands on top of each other .
You see similar tension when the maid is holding onto Dong-sik
with her hands clasped behind his back .
- Yes . - Those images are very closely connected .
But it also reminded me of a piano scene in my film , Stoker .
- I know which scene you mean . - It 's almost eerie .
And here is the same angle in the choir scene .
What I also find interesting is the bust of Beethoven 's head ,
which is looking down on everything . And the same thing is in his house .
- Yes , there it is . - And later on , that also takes on
a very important meaning in the film .
It is used as a small prop that connects the choir room and his house .
I was thinking how important Gyeong-hui is as a character ,
who is played by Ms. Um Aing-ran ,
but throughout the film , this Gyeong-hui character
hides behind the other characters .
She persuades two other female
characters to approach Dong-sik , and
one of them ends up killing herself .
- The one called Gwak Seon-Yeong . - Yes .
And the other woman is the maid .
From Dong-sik 's point of view , these two female characters
represent a displacement of his desire for Gyeong-hui .
- You mean more like a substitution for her . - Right .
Dong-sik is surrounded by too many women .
Um Aing-ran plays Gyeong-hui ...
- Yes , she plays Jo Gyeong-hui . - It is really difficult
to understand why she does what she does in the film .
So she is secretly in love with Dong-sik but cajoles her friend to write him a love letter .
- And because of the letter , she ends up killing herself . - Yes .
And she talks her into working as a maid for Dong-sik 's family .
Not only that , to get her to work as the maid for the family ,
she gives her 1,000 hwan ( the name of the previous Korean currency ) .
- Out of her own pocket . - Yes .
Why does she spend her own money to have the maid living in the house ,
and what does she gain from it ?
It is difficult to understand her motivation .
Since she works at a factory , she wouldn 't have a lot of money ,
but she takes private piano lessons ,
which she has to pay for .
Is she ingratiating herself with the family by spending money on them ,
or is she making the maid spy on the family for her ?
But she doesn 't ask the maid for information .
Gyeong-hui is a problematic character in the film .
If we were to look at the film from Dong-sik 's point of view ,
the target of his desire ,
the one he really desires is
Jo Gyeong-hui .
For example , the day he has sex with the maid
is the day when he couldn 't admit to himself his desire for Gyeong-hui .
He refuses to admit it , and that night , he is seduced by the maid .
- Yes . - Which leads to them having sex .
- And it is the day when they go to ... - To the grave
of Gwak Seon-Yeong . So there are three women that he becomes involved with .
It is the night when he gets entangled with all three women .
It is a fateful night .
Yes .
On the other hand , he is a family man .
He is making curry rice , which back then was called rice curry .
Yes .
So this choice of food , that he is making none other
than rice curry , which is a Western food ,
exemplifies a dream of the middle class ,
a dream that is illustrated by the two-story house and the rice curry .
Yes , the dream
is represented by those images .
Many critics pointed out that when this film was made in 1960 ,
it had not been that long ago that the country had
gone through war , and the economy was starting to be rebuilt .
It had been seven years since the war .
Critics saw how this family tried so hard to climb up the class ladder .
The middle class was represented by a two-story house and a piano .
And also by food like rice curry .
But not many people actually belonged to the middle class ; that was rare .
The people in this house wear shoes inside their house .
They do .
But Dong-sik 's wife only wears a traditional dress , the Hanbok .
She is the one with the strongest desire for success .
- But she is also the most conservative one . - She is .
This picture-perfect family can be violent sometimes .
When it comes to scenes like this , I have to say that director Kim ...
- This is when he wasn 't at his best . - Yes .
It is awkward to see them very loving towards each other .
- You feel that way ? - Yes , the way this scene was done seems very awkward .
The wife who wears a Hanbok all the time seems to symbolize
the attitude of the pre-modern .
It is the opposite of the character Gyeong-hui or the maid ,
who wears modern clothes , not to mention the fact that
the maid smokes .
They represent the ambition of or for modernity .
But the clash between these two differences in time results
in a tragedy .
At the same time , it is very complicated .
There are only a handful of characters in the film .
And they all have different sides to them , so it is difficult
to pinpoint and say that one character represents tradition , and one represents modernity .
For example , the maid is from the countryside ,
and she calls herself a second wife ,
which shows that her ideas and attitude are very
old-fashioned , almost feudalistic .
The wife , on the other hand , wants to buy a television
and send their children to college .
She is the one who is pursuing that desire to be middle class .
If you think about it , the mistress is someone who is between a wife and second wife .
In Kim Ki-young 's other film , Chungnyeo , the main character is a woman
whose mother was a second wife , and the film depicts in detail
the psychology of the main character , who is also fated to become a mistress .
The mistress character is a recurring one in Kim Ki-young 's films ,
which he built in different films that he directed .
- Yes . - The mistress character is a recurring character in his films .
Dong-sik just goes back and forth between the two women ,
and his indecisiveness is summarize in one line later in the film
when he says , " There was nothing I could do . "
Meaning that there was nothing he could do between his wife and his mistress .
Yes , and the maid comes into the house at the same time
when mice show up in the house .
The scene after that compares mice to squirrels .
The two animals are similar , but they are treated
very differently . One is the object of fear ...
- While the other is the object of affection . - Yes .
They exemplify the difference between the two women .
And the film also suggests how one is truer to her instincts
while the other is socialized or trained .
How many families do you think there were that wore shoes inside their house ?
- It was extremely rare . - Right .
And factory workers have time to
learn and sing in the choir .
They have a choir room and a teacher to teach them .
- A teacher paid by the company . - Yes , and he gets
paid enough to support his family of four .
And the factory workers are so well-dressed and Gyeong-hui
even gets private lessons . That all seems very unrealistic .
When you read books from the 60s or even from the time
of the Japanese colonial occupation , the dream of people from
the 1920s or 1930s always included a two-story house with a piano ,
which for them represented
what modernity or modern life must be like .
There is something about the word , " maid , " too .
Many young women who left their home in the countryside came to the city
and became factory workers or became kitchen maids called " sikmo . "
Yes , they were called " sikmo , " and the word " maid " was not used .
The word " maid " was not used even during the Joseon Dynasty , and
it was one of the words you would see in translation books .
Director Kim was famous for using literary expressions .
- He was . - So I think he used the word
intentionally , knowing that it was a very unfamiliar word .
And another reason that he wanted to use the word " Hanyeo " ( maid ) ,
besides the fact that it sounded very literary , must have been because
by using the syllable " ha , " meaning low ,
he wanted to bring a sense of spatialness to the word .
So it implies social class .
I think that is why he used the word " Hanyeo " instead of " sikmo . "
Director Kim was known to have been very proud of
the titles he came up with for his films .
After The Housemaid ( Hanyeo ) , he used the syllable " nyeo , "
meaning " woman , " in many of his films .
- He did . - Yes .
- One of his films is titled Woman of Water ( Sunyeo ) . - That 's right .
" Su " meaning water .
There was a film called Evil Woman ( Aknyeo ) , which he had been preparing
to shoot , but he passed away before he could even start filming it .
I think he came up with easy titles for his films ,
rather than coming up with good titles .
You 're right , because I really liked the title of his last film
that was released , Hunting for Idiots .
But I read an interview with Director Kim , in which he said
that he came up with the title because the film Declaration of an Idiot
and the song " Whale Hunting " were so popular at the time ,
so he just put them together for his film title , and it surprised
many people when they heard his explanation .
The titles that I like are The Housemaid ,
A Woman After a Killer Butterfly , and
Carnivorous Animal .
Aren 't they cool titles ?
They are , and you really like A Woman After a Killer Butterfly .
- I do . - That film is one of the strangest films that has ever been made .
It 's hard to make any sense from that film .
- It 's hard to figure out the story . - True .
The Housemaid is about a world that is very refined and
meticulously thought out , compared to his later films .
They were made under very different circumstances .
The films he directed later in career were produced
with a poor budget and in a limited time .
So Director Kim was not happy with the results .
He wasn 't .
Then what is it about A Woman After a Killer Butterfly
that you like so much ?
It 's not that I like everything about the film , but
Director Kim filmed it under such terrible conditions , almost to the point
that he didn 't care much about how the film ended up being ,
so he didn 't make the film to have a hit ;
he made the film just to hand it over to the company .
Within the given time .
Because he made the film without being concerned about anything ,
it actually shows to what extremes a director can go .
- You mean the film shows that . - Paradoxically ,
the film shows what happens when the director just lets go .
So it is hard to tell where the story is going , and
each scene seems so disjointed .
It is a film that lets you enjoy a director 's cinematic
imagination that is destructive and unbridled .
In this film , the maid seems to be
slightly slow .
- I am not sure . - Slightly .
I think you can see her that way , or see her as someone who is just weird .
She seems to go back and forth , which
leaves it to viewers to decide
what kind of person she is .
Sometimes she seems really sly , but
at other times she seems so naive , but
sometimes it seems every one of her actions has been calculated ,
or maybe she is just acting out of impulse .
When the wife tells her to have an abortion ,
she is so easily convinced by the wife .
And she really wants to depend
on the husband and the wife of the house .
She also comes across as someone who is very traditional , and
someone who think all she needs to have
- is the love of the husband . - She does .
But later in the film , she becomes afraid of being poisoned and replaces
the rat poison with sugar water , which shows how calculating she can be .
Yes , that part is very surprising .
Replacing the poison with sugar water is in Kim Ki-young 's other films .
In Woman of Fire and also in Hwa-nyuh of 82 .
- It 's one of the recurring motifs ... - Yes .
That the director uses .
Hwa-nyuh of 82 was the first Kim Ki-young film that I saw .
I saw it when it was released .
- In the theater ? - Yes .
I was a freshman in college , and it was one of the two films
that motivated me to become a film director .
- The other film was Hitchcock 's Vertigo . - I see .
- And Hwa-nyuh of 827 ? - Yes , Hwa-nyuh of 82 .
So I saw his latest film first , like many other people .
- Many people of our generation did . - That 's true .
It was the last remake of The Housemaid , which the director himself
made , and I ended up watching the original last .
I see .
The first Kim Ki-young film that I saw was Ban Geum-ryun .
- Really ? - I was in middle school .
But I couldn 't really understand the story .
Actually , I went to the theater to see something else playing at the theater at the time .
You know I was a middle school student at the time .
Well , it says so much about what kind of student you were .
She smokes a cigarette by breaking off the filter .
Do you suppose she does that
- to get a stronger taste ? - or , she does it
to smoke it more slowly ?
- The director was an ardent believer of Freud . - He was .
The way he uses the image of cigarettes in his films obviously
has s sexual meaning .
The way she breaks her cigarette into two seems very violent .
Yes , and because this film is from 1960 , which seems like a part of
the 1950s , and in the 50s , men used the expression " apres girls "
to label women that they were attracted to and feared at the same time .
" Apres girls , " meaning girls who presented an image of
of being unrestricted and free after the war ,
which was also represented by the image of them smoking .
The maid is smoking when she makes her first appearance in the film .
We did see her mopping but ...
Not counting those scenes ...
You mean the first scene when we can see her face .
Another important scene is the last one , which seems to end
with a moral lesson , but in the last scene dong-sik smokes .
Because the last scene reminds viewers
of previous smoking scenes , it gives you an eerie feeling .
The first scene here in which the maid is in the closet ,
she appears to be smoking . It had never been seen before in a film ,
and it must have been shocking to the audience at the time .
It seems to flaunt the image of the femme fatale
that is hiding behind you .
It is not clear in the film , but I think it is possible to speculate
that Gyeong-hui is using cigarettes
as a way to control the maid .
- Yes , that seems possible . - And she has a line ...
- She does . - She says the line that
there was a reason why she taught her how to smoke .
She is able to control her with one cigarette , which implies the hierarchical order ...
- Or exploitation ? - Yes .
The film is definitely making a statement about the class order
in the factory and in society .
That is true .
In the film , there is no sexual feeling between
Dong-sik and his wife .
There isn 't , but still , you have a scene like the one we are looking at now .
The scene between him and his wife is depicted this way here ,
but when you watch the two remakes of the original that Kim directed ,
the wife tries really hard to seduce her husband .
Yes , but in this film , the wife is pregnant , so it seems
inappropriate to show any sexual feeling between them .
Yes , and the sexual feeling has been all given to the young women .
I am not sure if this room where the choir practices
is a studio or a movie set , or if they borrowed
an auditorium and dressed it up as a set ,
but the wall is so ...
The director decorated the wall in a bizarre way .
The house , too . Dong-sik 's house has very strange patterns
on the wall .
In this scene , he covered the wall with cloth , but it is not a curtain ,
and the cloth has creases . In this black and white film , without
any colors , the creases provide an accentuated sense of texture ,
and it makes the scene visually enriching but also scary .
The visual design of the choir room seems to be
- very expressionistic . - It does .
It does give a very strong impression of being expressionistic .
With the lights , too .
The sequence of scenes seems very modern .
As soon as they hear the news that Gwak Seon-Yeong has died ,
the camera marches straight to the corridor , the train whizzes by , and
they are already at her grave . The scenes move very fast and
very effectively , too . And at the grave , there is rain and lightning .
So the film sets the mood for the fateful night right away .
Yes , and the story takes place basically at two different places :
the two-story house
and the factory .
But this part of the film was shot on a real location , not on a set ,
and the place is in the countryside .
The funeral was intentionally shot at this location and added in the film .
This scene shows where women like factory workers
and the maid come from .
- Yes . - What social background they have .
- In a way . - True .
The scene shows us that .
Here , you see Dong-sik 's house , and the film repeatedly shows
that the house is next to the railroad .
When Gyeong-hui goes to the house , and Dong-sik is going back home ,
the film always shows the railroad in the backdrop .
You can hear the train in the house , and it makes you think about
how the train carries young girls from the countryside
to the city .
It also makes you compare the train to the desire
that is speeding and heading towards its end .
And the train scene is also used to indicate a scene change
and to indicate that time has passed .
The train scene in the film seems to have
an image of regression rather than an image of moving forward
- when you look at the line of its movement . - Right .
So the train scene also symbolizes
an image of transgression .
Why do you think Dong-sik resisted Gyeong-Hui 's seduction ?
I think she is the girl that he desires most , but
Gwak Seon-yeong 's death must have triggered a sense of fear in him ,
and because the factory is his work place , any scandal
would lead to a detrimental result financially .
Yes , I thought about that , too .
And he is getting paid by Gyeong-hui for the lessons .
And because he works at the factory , he has become
entangled with Gyeong-hui
- in many ways . - He has .
This is the second funniest scene in the film .
This is like the worst soap drama , with the woman who is
- ripping her own clothes off . - All By herself .
While she is doing that , he is saying she should continue to come for her lessons .
Even at that moment , he is worried about money .
So he finally sends her away only to be faced with another temptation .
There she is without a bra ,
and her hair is down for the first time .
Yes , she always had it braided until this scene .
The way Lee Eun-sim plays the maid character here by covering
her own breasts is just so ingenious .
The way she blinks her eyes seems so amazingly modern , too .
She seems embarrassed and so brazen at the same time
because she does it while staring at him .
She is covering her breasts , but not her nipples .
In the next scene , she is covering her nipples , but
when you really think about it , covering them seems
more provocative than not covering them .
This scene is also similar to a scene in Thirst . In the scene , the actress ,
- Kim Ok-bin says , " I 'm very shy . " - She does .
In that scene , she says it while touching her breasts .
- And there is another scene with a cigarette . - Yes .
This scene is also up to interpretation .
This is one of the most important scenes in the film .
The way she rolls her eyes like that .
- Her acting ... - It 's impressive .
She must have acted following the director 's suggestions .
- Don 't you think ? - Yes , I think so .
Kim Ki-young was a director who had to have
his way about everything .
- The scene here ... - Yes ?
When I saw it for the first time , I thought when he touched the maid ,
he had succumbed to the maid 's seduction , but when I saw it a second time ,
I realized that might not be the case .
He is trying to leave , but
she blocks the window and closes it . She is blocking him .
So he is actually pushing her away
to get her out of his way . It could be the reason
why he touched her .
So he touches her , but the maid squeezes her arms
with his hands under her armpits
as if she has put handcuffs on him .
After she makes sure that he can 't move ,
she puts her feet on top of his shoes .
Even at that point , Dong-sik looks like he wants to leave .
The maid 's seduction is much more aggressive than I remembered ,
and Dong-sik just gets dragged into the next situation .
It made me think that maybe I was influenced by this film
because in my films Sympathy for Mr. Vengeance and Thirst ,
there are scenes in which a woman 's arm and legs are
wrapped around a man 's body .
In Sympathy for Mr. Vengeance , there is a scene in which a girl
has her legs tightly around her father like the one in this film .
Most of the male characters in Director Kim 's films are
incompetent and indecisive .
They are not the bread - winner of their family ,
and they often depend
on their wife financially .
In comparison , the wives in his films have very specific jobs .
For example , the main female character in Woman of Fire and
Hwa-nyuh of 82 own a chicken farm .
In this film , the wife makes clothes with her sewing machine .
But the husband in Kim 's films is either an artist or
an intellectual of some sort .
- That is often the case . - Yes .
So the man claims to be an artist , but
- all he does is create trouble . - He does .
In this film , the husband gives the impression of being
incompetent , indecisive , and inept , but
if you watch the film more carefully , he proves to be quite violent , too .
- He beats up the women . - Quite often , yes .
Especially Gyeong-hui and the maid in this film .
- But he doesn 't touch his wife . - No .
In this film , when he slaps a woman ,
she falls flat on the floor , which creates , again ,
the spatial image of who is on top and who is on the bottom .
And the camera angle has the man looking down and the woman looking up .
Yes , and the house is also structured that way .
The maid 's room and the husband 's piano are on the second floor .
The wife 's sewing machine is on the first floor , and the first floor is
contrasted to the second floor . And the space that the two women
share is the kitchen .
And you can 't tell where the children 's rooms are
even if you watch the movie very carefully .
Later in the film , when the husband is forced to sleep
in the maid 's room , the girl sleeps
with her mother .
- After the boy dies . - Yes .
Until that point , the film doesn 't let you know where the children sleep .
When they were building the second floor and shooting the scenes there ,
they must have considered the line of movement a lot .
Now , the maid moves into the veranda to peep into the next room ,
and that line of her movement is very important .
The film does not show you where this house is located , but
watching some scenes shot on location , I believe they found a house
that they already had in mind , and with that as the model ,
they must have built the set accordingly .
When they looked for a possible model for the house ,
they must have known exactly what they wanted
because the maid 's room is connected to Dong-sik 's room
not from inside the house , but from the outside .
So they can go into the rooms through the door , but they can
also go in or peep inside through the window .
And the film uses this layout to the maximum .
That 's right , and there are so many scenes shot from outside of the window .
And by using those mis-en - scenes in the film ,
it shows how
trapped these characters feel .
The tracking shot was used to show the connection between
the two rooms , or to show a movement that either
goes forward or backward .
But the tracking shot scenes that show how the two rooms are connected
are really impressive .
And they are emphasized in the film .
The scene here , to me , is almost like a fly in the ointment .
It is not really necessary , and
it also is not interesting .
The film wants to show how lost Dong-sik feels
by putting him outside the house in a changed scenery .
For me , this scene and the taxi scene that follow
- reminds of a scene from Aimless Bullet . - I know which scene you mean .
- Especially the taxi scene here . - You 're right .
The driver says , " He came into my cab like an aimless bullet "
And like in Aimless Bullet , there isn 't a place that he wants to go to .
He says , " Take me anywhere . "
He does .
The bartender shaking the bottle like that , don 't you think it has a meaning ?
It does have a lot of sexual meaning .
The acting here can be seen as a bit conventional .
Their lines are also a bit awkward and so is their acting .
Back then , directors must have had tremendous difficulty
shooting sex scenes .
The film showed her feet when she stepped on his shoes .
- You mean her bare feet . - Yes .
Things like that enable viewers to feel and imagine so much more .
We know how Hitchcock got away
with censorship from so many examples .
Director Kim also overcame censorship by using
very creative images that are compact with meaning .
In a way , censorship made them more creative .
- By having restrictions . - Right .
In Billy Wilder 's Some Like It Hot , when Marilyn Monroe
kisses Tony Curtis ,
- he spreads his legs up in the air . - He does .
A scene like that illustrates the physical reaction that is
happening to the man , in an indirect way .
Everything in this film is so compact with meaning ,
with everything being calculated and nothing that is unnecessary ,
so the slight inadequacy in the bar scene that we just saw
seems to stand out .
I think it 's because other scenes are so exceptional that
the bar scene seems like it was an extra attached to the film .
- You mean like an additional modifier . - Yes .
Now we find out that the maid is pregnant .
If you were to look at Woman of Fire and Hwa-nyuh of 82 ,
which were Kim Ki-young 's own remakes of The Housemaid ,
and Carnivorous Animal , which is considered to be the remake of
- Chungnyeo ... - Carnivorous Animal , yes .
In all five films , the man is
like a territory , and two women are standing on
opposite sides and are engaged in a serious battle
over the territory , while the man just waits for
them to decide what they are going to do with him .
That 's right , but what is funny is that the man is just a territory ,
but he thinks he is reigning over these women .
He holds on to to his desire to rule over the women .
Dong-sik seemed to be just a music teacher who teaches
the choir and gives piano lessons , but here he has a pencil
in his hand while playing the piano .
- He is a composer . - We find out now that
he is a composer .
In the director 's other films after this one , the husband continues
- to be a composer . - He does .
The wife 's job changes , but the husband is always a composer .
That 's right .
The biggest difference between The Housemaid and Woman of Fire
and Hwa-nyuh of 82 is that in this film , the maid seduces the man ,
but in the other two films , the women are raped by the man .
That is a big difference .
All the doors in this house are
sliding doors .
Which is different from the houses from this time , and
they also contribute to making this scene quite unique .
The patterns on the wall look like a spider 's web or a beehive .
They do .
And the sliding doors really capture the psychology of the characters
in this small space
very effectively .
If the doors were not sliding but hinged , you would have a problem
with the camera angle if you wanted to show
a person behind or by the door .
But with sliding doors , it is a matter of how much you have the door
open to show the person behind it , even from the front angle .
That 's so right .
Also , when actors open or close a door , they have a very limited space ,
but once they push a door open , the space opens up for them to act in .
- Or when they pull a door open . - Yes .
But with the doors in this film , you just have to slide them open .
So the actors can close or open them really fast , or they can stand
very close to each other with only the door between them .
Without any unnecessary movement .
So when you slide it closed , the open space suddenly
becomes like a wall .
You saw white women dancing on TV , which has
now changed into a doll that looks like a white woman .
This scene is related to dreams that many Koreans had
at the time , the people who were not a part of the middle class .
We mentioned the symbolic meaning of curry rice .
- Yes . - And also the meaning of a two-story house .
And a piano .
That , too .
They are all related .
One of the things that Director Kim was very concerned with
- was the lighting in the film . - Right .
If you take a closer look at the lighting , you do see problems .
For example , where is the source of the light ?
And you can see that the director used the lighting the way he wanted .
Even in scenes done in broad daylight ,
you see several shadows of a character at once ,
sometimes two or three shadows at a time , which makes
- no logical sense . - No .
So you see that sometimes in his films ,
but it is obvious that Director Kim was more interested in
- illustrating characters ' emotions . - You mean with the visual effect of lighting .
Yes , that was more important to him .
And he also had a very keen sense when it came to discovering new actors .
He did .
He usually had star actors in his films .
He did , but at the same time , he always found
new faces for important roles in his films .
He did .
Lee Eun-sim , who played the maid in the film , and Yoon Yeo-jeong ,
- for example ... - And Lee Hwa-si .
Ah , Lee Hwa-si .
- The legendary actress . - Yes .
He discovered all these actresses .
Even Park Jung-ja .
For the first time .
Kim Ji-mi , too .
- And Moon Hee , too . - That 's right .
- He was the one who discovered these actresses . - He discovered
talented actresses who went on to become stars , and
he was famous as a director who made actresses into stars .
It 's hard to imagine now , but Kim Ki-young was a director
who produced box office hits .
According to records , he was the one who directed the biggest
box office hits in 1971 and 1972 .
They were Woman of Fire and Chungnyeo .
Everyone in our parents ' generation knew him , and they all knew
his films , such as The Housemaid , Woman of Fire , and Chungnyeo .
And his last film , which was released in 1984 , and
we often talk about how he and his films were rediscovered
at BIFF in 1997 .
You wonder how this director , who produced cinematic masterpieces ,
could become so forgotten in the course of 13 years .
In some aspects , he did it to himself
by making B-movies after
his film Transgression .
I really liked some of his films that he made after this one ,
but critics and the media turned their backs on his films ,
and he also slowly became forgotten by the audience .
And wasn 't he famous for being eccentric and
not caring at all about how people in the industry thought of him ?
- Well , there are legendary stories about him . - True .
He was famous for saying he was the only one who had the answer ,
or that he cooked beef in secret and ate it all by himself .
You saw the scene in which the wife , played by Ju Jeung-nyeo ,
throws the TV and sewing machine . She was one of the top actresses at the time .
According to records that I had found , she was the owner of
a film production company under her own name two or three years before making this film .
- Really ? - Yes , in the 50s .
So she was an actress who also had power in the production aspect .
She was one of the most popular actresses at the time , and
even compared to Lee Eun-sim , her acting is just as intense .
True .
Towards the end of the film , she is scarier than other characters .
She is .
The wife is the character who goes through
the biggest changes in the story .
Compared to her indecisive husband , she makes the important
decisions at crucial moments .
Sometimes her decisions seem criminal or sometimes she uses persuasion ,
- but she knows almost instinctively ... - She does .
That she has to survive .
And in order to survive , she makes swift decisions .
And in the director 's series of films , the one who survives is the wife .
Yes .
In the scene we have here ...
She looks so delicate and pretty .
She is walking up the stairs in a white ramie dress with the light
shining on her from the side , and when she lifts her skirt like that ,
she looks as if she is about to dance .
She goes up to the second floor , and the contrast here is quite grotesque .
The wife in a pretty white dress is standing next to the maid , who is
banging on the piano .
Lee Eun-sim was only 19 at the time .
I believe she was in one other film before making this one .
But after getting so much attention for this film ,
she didn 't make that many movies after it .
- She was in a few movies . - Two or three , I believe .
And we have only the titles of those movies .
Another aspect of this film that surprises us
is the way it uses sound .
Considering Korean films at the time , this film definitely stands out
for its visual aspect , and at this time , people did not pay much
attention to sound ; however , in this film , the sounds are
loaded with meanings .
There is the sound of the sewing machine ,
the sound of the piano , and the sound of the train passing by ,
or the sound of the girl walking up the stairs with crutches .
There is also the creaking sound from the stairs .
And later , the film has the sound of the maid 's head banging on the stairs .
That is the most shocking sound .
And these sounds are all part of the narrative , meaning that
Director Kim did not finish filming the movie and then thought about
how to mix the sound by trying different means of editing .
- He knew from the beginning . - From the beginning , it was done as planned .
- He had a definite plan how to use sound . - He did .
For example , in the scene in which the husband confesses that he had an affair .
And the woman is pregnant . The wife asks , " Who is the woman ? "
- And you hear the sound of the piano . - You do .
When they hear the banging on the piano from upstairs ,
the wife says , " So she is the one . "
So they don 't have to talk more about it .
We have another crucial scene here .
On the top of the stairs , she stands there as a scary
silhouette , in spite of the fact that she is out of focus .
If you think about it , this is the most important scene in the film .
- But they close the door . - They do .
They only allude to what is about to happen , and you only hear the sound .
And when they open the door , you see the famous scene shot from above .
It is the famous scene .
The characters and the camera move backward , and the door
is closed to create more space .
The line is drawn between the two different classes of people .
- Yes , the camera shows the outside again . - It really is one of the best scenes ever .
It is .
I remember seeing similar scenes in Woman of Fire
and Hwa-nyuh of 82 .
It is so cleanly done , without losing any of the shocking impact .
It makes you imagine by not showing it to you .
- It is so elegantly done . - It is .
This scene in which Dong-sik is carrying the maid upstairs later becomes
the scene in which she is clinging to his leg .
- As they come down . - It makes a contrast .
The way they enter the room is really similar to
the way the maid dies at the end .
And here , Kim Jin-kyu 's acting is just superb .
He looks so sick and tired and doesn 't know what to do .
- He must hate himself so much . - And wondering how he
got himself in this mess .
My wife laughed so much at this scene .
When you think about it , the most important year in Korean
film history was the year between the April Revolution in 1960
and the May Coup in 1961 .
In Hollywood , they consider the most important time in the Hollywood
film industry to be between 1939 and 1940 , when films like
Gone with the Wind , The Wizard of Oz , and Citizen Kane came out .
In Korea , the masterpieces by the so - called three most
important directors were all made in 1960 :
this film , Mother and a Guest ,
and Aimless Bullet .
The maid is coaxed by the wife to abort her baby , which
the maid carries out almost immediately .
She does .
The story moves so fast that viewers might feel uneasy .
What makes Kim Ki-young 's films so interesting is the fact that
they are so unpredictable .
That 's true .
And his films become more and more so .
His later films , you mean .
The story keeps heading towards somewhere which seems unimaginable ,
but as viewers follow the story , they will ask themselves
what they would have done if they were in the character 's position .
What would one do if he was seduced like Dong-sik ?
Then , you get to understand , caught between the two women ,
how he just doesn 't know what to do . The film is
able to draw out sympathetic reactions from its viewers .
So the story is not so preposterous , and it makes viewers
identify with the characters . Compared to films from its time ,
however , it takes the story in a very different direction .
When the wife is walking up the stairs , she passes the maid
as if she is looking at a cockroach . She is afraid that
her dress might touch her .
It looks very cruel .
The wife treats the maid the way she reacted to seeing the mouse in the house .
She does .
What 's interesting about the scene is that it ends
without any sense of conclusion .
The maid is crying and clinging onto the wife ,
the wife is screaming out , " Honey , honey , help me ! "
And the husband is just pulling his hair out .
The scene just ends without showing how everything ends .
And there is the sound of a train passing by .
And it is a loud sound .
The sound is overlayed onto the scene .
So the maid loses her baby , but
the wife gives birth to her baby .
That 's what happens .
The maid is resentful because they care so much about their baby
while she was forced to kill her own baby .
Yes , that is really scary .
That is what makes this film so scary .
And it is known that this film is based on a real story .
- Did it happen in Gimcheon ? - Yes .
There was a real murder of a five-year-old boy . A woman
who was involved with a man drowned his son .
And this film is based on that real murder .
This is another strange scene because it is just chaotic
in the house , and in the midst of it , the wife gives birth ,
but the husband was out while his wife was having their baby .
And he comes back home as if it were no big deal ,
and you wouldn 't think that he would pay more attention
to his pet than to his own baby .
He comes into the room and doesn 't even look at his wife .
This is a scene that makes you wonder
what 's going on in his head .
Kim Ki-young occupies such an important place in
Korean film history because before him ,
films were considered simply as a vehicle for a story ,
meaning films were just another way to tell a story .
- Only a means to tell a story . - Yes .
But Kim is very important in film history because his films began
from ideas that were so divergent from that understanding of films .
You cannot say that this is a realistic film .
This film is definitely different from other films from that time ,
but you cannot say that it completely disregards the logical coherence
of the story .
In that aspect , what do you think about those points
in Kim 's films that could have been smoothed out , but
are shown in a quite crude manner ?
Sometimes I do feel that he did go slightly overboard in his films ,
but at least in The Housemaid , although he does tell a violent story ,
it really doesn 't have that many logical problems
compared to his other films .
The children in this film are also interesting .
They are not like normal children in other films .
Especially the boy .
The boy , played by Ahn Sung-ki , is really mean and ill-mannered .
- He is a terrible boy . - He really is .
But the way he is depicted might be close to how boys are at that age .
There are some boys who are like him .
How realistic the boy should be portrayed was up to the director ,
but if you look at it from a class difference ,
even the children have no respect for the maid .
They use her , but at the same time , they are afraid of her .
They have an unreasonable fear of the maid
from the beginning , saying she would use the rat poison on them .
You wonder why they are so afraid of her , and
why they think she is such a person of importance in the house .
And it is not about who is nice and who is bad .
The boy seems meaner , and the girl seems as if she would
understand the maid , but she doesn 't at the end .
And she says let 's not deal with someone who is crazy .
You can see how hostile these children are
towards the maid .
The way the femme fatale is treated in this film is
different from other film noir .
Of course , because this is not a film noir .
The way this film sees the maid character is ...
how should I put it ...
- it is very ambiguous . - It is .
The film sees her as someone who should be vanquished .
Like a villainess .
On the other , it really takes a deeper look into the character .
Yes , the film makes you sympathetic towards her after she loses her baby .
It is also because the people in the house are just as mean and evil .
True .
They do become more and more evil .
The man makes her have a baby and the woman makes her lose that baby .
Makes her lose the baby .
- It 's such a famous line . - It is .
Because the film sums it up so nicely for viewers , they have no choice
but to nod their heads and say that it is true .
And the way Kim Jin-kyu acts in the scene is quite vicious .
Looking like a character from a gangster film , he comes in
with his eyes cast on the floor , and suddenly he slaps her .
And usually when people slap someone ,
their hand comes from the outside and goes in , but
he slaps her from inside out .
- So the way his hand snaps looks strange . - It does .
And they leave her like that when she has been starving for
three days , and bleeding , too .
After they force to lose her baby ,
they make her eat like a cat eating trash on the street
or a mouse in the sewer .
By showing her in that state , the film confuses viewers
as to which character they should identify with ,
and who they should side with .
An angle like that is impossible in real life .
Because there is a wall behind the cupboard .
We use scenes like that one nowadays when we are
shooting someone opening a refrigerator or microwave .
The director used it in this film .
He was not hesitant at all to use a camera angle like that .
The scene in which the maid is carrying the water is really strange , too .
- It is a very intense scene . - It is .
I think this scene was probably influenced by Hitchcock .
Or Akira Kurosawa .
I 'm sure he was also influenced by Japanese films , too .
Like Shohei Imamura .
According to records , there was no director who knew film
trends better than Kim Ki-young at the time .
I 'm sure .
People in Korea did not have many opportunities to watch Japanese films .
Especially compared to American and European movies that were released .
Director Kim lived in Japan for a couple of years .
- He did . - And he was fluent in Japanese .
He went to Japan even in the 90s to
watch films .
The story is so twisted here . It makes you think about
how the director is seeing this maid .
She causes the boy to die , but she doesn 't kill him by feeding him
the rat poison . He thinks she did , so he becomes so shocked that
he runs down the stairs and dies .
It seems the director did not want to make the maid
into a complete monster .
That 's true , and the one who really carries out her plan to murder
the maid is actually the wife .
- She does . - She puts the rat poison in the soup .
The maid only plays a game with the poison .
She scares the boy by drinking the water and spitting it back out .
But in the director 's remakes of this film , the boy is actually thrown
by the maid and is killed .
She does .
When you think about the scene , you can see how Im Sang-soo
was also very influenced by Kim Ki-young .
- Like that scene in ... - Yes , of course .
In A Good Lawyer 's Wife ,
there is the scene in which a boy is killed .
And Im Sang-soo also directed a remake of The Housemaid .
He did .
Now viewers might wonder
where the story is going to go now .
The boy just falls down from the stairs and dies .
He does .
When you think that this must be the ending ,
the wife says let 's not do anything about their boy 's death .
For me , this is the strangest part
of the story .
She just saw her own boy die in front of her eyes , but
she tells her husband not to report it and to go on to work
because if he gets fired , they won 't be able to make a living .
Holding her dead son and looking like the statue of Pieta
with tears in her eyes , she looks up to the camera upstairs ,
and she delivers that line which doesn 't seem possible .
It really is a very , very strange turn in the story .
But if viewers were able to follow the story up to this point ,
- they should be able to understand her decision . - True .
Because her character has been set up that way ,
viewers are able to accept her decision here .
As always , everything is connected to desire and money
in Kim 's films , and even in this twist of the story ,
the connection to money is emphasized .
This film is really compulsive .
It keeps on using the stairs ,
the doors are slid open and closed , and it continues to use
the recurring tracking shots ,
and the piano and other props .
They are repeated to the point that you could get
- tired of them . - They are repeated again and again .
They are repeated , but
they are not boring or monotonous .
They are meticulously calculated to fit in perfectly
into different situations . The eye contact doesn 't work here .
Dong-sik looks in a different direction .
It 's no big deal , though .
Their eyes do not meet .
In this film , you see mice , but in Kim 's remakes of this film ,
he uses chickens .
He uses mice and chickens .
The wife 's leg has pins and needles , but the Korean expression
uses the word " mouse " " to describe it . And it happens
because she worked too hard on the sewing machine .
So you have a scene in which the husband massages her leg .
- It is a funny scene . - Slightly funny , yes .
The director must have chosen mice or chicken because
they symbolize fertility .
Fertility or virility is connected to the sexual desire
in his films .
Now you see the girl planning to harm
the maid .
It could be because the maid caused the boy to die .
I don 't know who played this girl character , but
she was really cast well for the role .
Her face is not a face of a girl , and her expressions , too .
She looks like a woman except that her body is small .
She garners sympathy because she limps , but
she always looks sad , which plays a key role
in making this family
look very unstable .
She is the one who makes the family look
unstable from the very beginning of the film .
Now the relationship between the maid and the wife
- has reversed . - It has .
And it shows how it became reversed .
And you don 't get to see a man who is that pathetic .
Dong-sik doesn 't decide to go to the maid 's room ,
or because he is sexually drawn to the woman .
He goes up because his wife tells him to go up .
- So he goes up . - He does .
Throughout the entire film , he only makes one decision on his own ,
which is to die together with the maid .
- Even then ... - That is the only one .
Even then the maid tells him that
- he has to die with her . - If not , she says
she will kill his wife . So he makes a decision .
But he was pushed to even make that decision .
The maid says to choose whether he should die or his wife .
You can say he does make a big decision to end his life ,
but he was forced to decide .
This reversal of power in a relationship between one man
and two women is often introduced in Kim 's films .
In Chungnyeo , for example , the wife lets her husband
stay with a prostitute ] mistress to cure his impotency ,
and to do that , she even buys the mistress a house .
The wife does .
But at a certain point in the story , the two women decide to share
the man , one has him before midnight and the other after midnight .
You can always find a moment like this one in Kim 's films .
This is also a very bizarre scene .
She bites him on his shoulder .
And later she covers him with her hair .
She covers his face with her hair .
She has her legs wrapped around his legs .
It 's hard to figure out the meaning of her actions .
They are really bizarre .
She looks like a snake .
Or , the image seems to say that by covering him with her hair ,
she wants to devour him and be one with him .
In that scene , even the legs of the chair give you a powerful impression .
They do .
She looks like she is about to eat him .
Or , she is trying to cover up his humiliation .
If you take it further , you can get to images in a vampire film .
Now the bizarre scene cuts to the handle of the sewing machine .
What Kim does in a scene like this one is that
when characters have a change of mind , they don 't say it out loud ,
but instead , they perform a specific action , like
holding the scissors in this case .
He tries to show you the changes that are taking place
in his characters through these actions .
- But she doesn 't use the scissors . - She doesn 't .
What is so carefully done here is that when the wife
wants to kill the maid , she can 't find the rat poison .
But when she looks for either salt or pepper and opens the cupboard ,
she finds the rat poison sitting there .
That 's when she decides again to kill her .
It also gives you the impression that it was fated that way .
The rat poison wasn 't there because the maid took it .
It was used to kill the squirrel , and then
it was switched .
Unlike the sliding doors in the house , you have to pull the door
of the cupboard , which gives you a different feeling altogether .
It does .
I didn 't think about it before , but it really does .
The fear in this film is created by things
you drink or eat .
- Things you can 't do without . - You have to eat and drink .
Right .
Because it makes it scary for you to eat or drink ,
the fear seems so primal and real .
There is a scene in which the children refuse to eat for two days ,
and the maid feeds them rice by force .
In films from other countries ...
This scene here ...
Yes ...
It 's such a strange scene .
It 's like a scene from a Hitchcock or De Palma film .
They are a mother and a daughter .
- They are not hostile to each other . - They are on the same side .
And they want the same thing .
But the girl 's stare ...
The wife has to carry out her plan to kill the maid
while her daughter is watching her , and the sense of guilt that this must create ...
It is so surprising to see a scene like this one in a Korean film from 1960 .
Also , the scene in which the maid takes the girl 's father to her room
- in front of her . - Again , in a movie from 1960 .
That is quite shocking , too .
The girl looks pleadingly at her father and tells him not to go with the maid .
But the wife tells him to go .
And the girl says , " Dad , but don 't drink the water . "
She does .
That is the moment when you are not sure whether
you should laugh or cry .
The scene in which I laughed really loudly was when the maid
calls him " Honey " out of the blue after having sex .
She calls him " Honey , " but the man is so startled , and he says
" Don 't call me anything ! "
She calls herself Dong-sik 's second wife , and he doesn 't know
what to do with her , which just makes you laugh .
It really is a scary moment .
A nightmarish moment for any married man .
But it can make the audience laugh .
The positioning of the characters and the way they are dressed
are making a clear contrast here .
Yes .
The maid is the only one in a black dress .
Here , the maid is making a case : at least the wife has the hope
of saving her husband and her family .
However , the maid doesn 't have even that .
It makes you nod your head .
The wife has everything to lose .
Right .
But the maid has nothing to lose now .
Which is why they are able to go at each other .
Now , the wife is obsessed with working at her sewing machine .
In Kim 's films , you have men who are dominated by
and dependent on their wife 's
financial ability .
Some see that as a projection of
Kim 's own personal relationship with his wife .
People do talk about that , but there is really
- no way for us to know for sure . - It really was between them .
Kim 's wife was a dentist .
Yes .
And she was financially responsible for the family .
And Kim only cared for his vision of art .
He did .
She provided for him .
And people say that they were very happy in their marriage .
Yes .
It was a tragedy , but they did
pass away together .
There are those things on the table and the piano .
- You see scenes like this one often in this film . - We do .
A scene like this one really exudes the feel
of a horror film .
It is also because of the music .
He could have used other music here , but he consistently uses
similar , horror-sounding music that uses only horn instruments ,
percussion , and piano . And he rarely uses
string instruments .
He really doesn 't use string instruments .
The music is really unnerving .
The music does not hesitate to shock you .
The maid made a threat to the children and made it look like
she would feed them with poison , but she doesn 't .
She didn 't do that to the boy .
Or to the girl .
The film seems very violent and cruel , and
the maid really seems like a villainess , but in spite of all that ,
you do feel for her .
It is a film that maintains a sense of integrity by
portraying the characters with a sense of humanity .
According to records , this film as well as Woman of Fire
were such big hits at the time , and the audiences were so engrossed
with the films that they screamed in the middle of them ,
- " Kill that bitch ! " - Yes , I read that , too .
That it happened very often .
Many middle-class families at the time had a maid .
So there were many similar cases as the story of this film .
I 'm sure there were .
And the expression " second wife " wasn 't so odd at the time .
I 'm sure many women in the audience had an instinctive
fear of it .
I found this scene sad .
Looking at this scene , the maid here has no thought of killing herself .
She is eating because she wants to live , and because of this scene ,
it becomes quite sad
when she finally decides to kill herself .
At crucial moments in the film , it always rains .
The night when Dong-sik succumbs to the maid 's seduction ,
lightning strikes a tree .
- Yes . - And the smoke from the tree
symbolizes the sex between the two .
This is another strange scene .
What I find most interesting about the film is the way it uses
the character Gyeong-hui .
The maid really feels this intense jealousy not towards the wife ,
but towards Gyeong-hui .
I think there is even a saying about that ...
The maid used to call her , " Sister , " but she doesn 't anymore .
This is the last time we see Gyeong-hui .
Yes .
The way Gyeong-hui leaves the scene is quite interesting , too .
The maid brings cigarettes when she didn 't have to , and
she reminds her of the memories related to cigarettes .
Like the way the wife grabbed the scissors , the maid drops the plates ,
and one of them breaks , and
- now she has a knife in her hand . - And it gives her
ideas , which she carries out .
- If the plates didn 't break ... - Right ...
Following the logical process of the scene ...
- And that awkward way she re-enters the room . - With her body lowered .
We saw the bars in the window in the tracking shot , and
she looks like a predator .
Like a Carnivorous Animal from one of Kim 's film titles .
The scene which shows the characters this close up is the first in this film .
Before this , we saw a possibility of the family continuing
their life as if they have somehow come to terms
with their positioning in the power balance , but
this is the moment when that is shattered .
- The tension is reignited . - It is .
Now it is heading towards an end that cannot be reversed .
Gyeong-hui is injured and runs away from the house .
She could be going to the police or
to the factory and say what took place at Dong-sik 's house .
So they would have to face it somehow .
Right .
They even hid the cause of their son 's death ,
and tried so hard to hide the maid as the family secret ,
but now it might be
known to the outside .
Which is why the director had the close - up scene on the maid 's face .
- The closest one in the film . - Right .
So there was a reason why
that the scene that shows the characters this close up was necessary in the film .
What is difficult to understand here is ...
Aren 't those shadows just fantastic ?
What is difficult to understand here is why the maid
is looking at Beethoven 's bust as she is dying .
Is she looking at it just to show that she is dying by
how the bust becomes blurry ?
Or , is Beethoven 's bust a prop that symbolizes
the fact that this is a middle - class family with an artist father
and that this family is familiar with Western culture ?
Is that a prop that symbolizes all those ideas ?
But you see it becoming blurry as the maid looks at it here .
Yes .
The maid is told not to touch the piano , but
she keeps pestering him to teach her the piano .
When she first comes into the family , she says she wants
to learn how to sew from the wife .
But at some moment , she says she wants to learn the piano
like Gyeong-hui .
In short , she is expressing her desire for something that she shouldn 't desire .
And that something is symbolized by Beethoven ,
which is why she sees the bust while being choked .
But you see the traditional masks
- above the piano . - Yes , there are a couple of them .
The masks used in the mask dance .
Do you think the director used them to create an eerie feeling ?
I don 't know . There are dolls in the room , too .
Yes , there are a lot of things in this room .
The scene shows Dong-sik 's arms hanging helplessly like that
from the window . It is pouring rain and his arms look so helpless .
It is a scene that
- visually summarizes the film . - Visually , it does .
That one image .
Now is the climax of the film .
Yes .
Up to this point , the audience is wondering whether the poison is real .
The maid could have switched it with sugar water .
She switched it once so why not a second time .
So that could be poison or not , and she said to drink it together ,
- but she could drink it alone . - Right .
If one of them doesn 't drink it , who would it be ?
She already used this trick with the children .
So the audience must be remembering that it happened before .
They were tricked a couple of times in the film .
Viewers have to watch this scene wondering
whether they are really drinking the poison
or if both of them would drink it .
If we were to think about it , wouldn 't we think
that the maid would drink it first ?
I did , too , but
- in the film , it is the opposite . - Right .
So viewers now would think she is not going to drink it .
She is such a cunning woman .
Now Dong-sik talks to the maid as if
- he understands her for the first time . - He does .
And what the film has developed up to this point , the tricks
that she has played and the turns and twists in the story , is coming together .
What the maid says here is really inconsistent .
She says she wants to live with him forever in heaven .
But she also says what good is happiness when you are dead .
You can be happy only when you 're alive .
So she ends up contradicting what she said before .
It 's like the last line in your film , Thirst .
It is .
And a moment later she says if they are not together now ,
she won 't be able to have him even in heaven , so
she tries to stop him
from going to his wife .
She seems to be just rambling .
Their hands clasped ...
It is one of the most impressive scenes in the film .
They have to unclasp their hands for her to give him a cigarette .
In the film , the image of hands is very important .
Like the hand that turns the sewing machine .
The hand that holds a smoke or plays the piano .
And finally the hands that are clasped .
The night when they had sex for the first time , her hands were clasped
behind his back . Her hands look so determined , like the hands
of the famous Nongae , who killed a Japanese general by clasping
her hands around him and jumping to their death .
The clasped hands manifest the joining of their desires .
As in the case when Gyeong-hui is taking her piano lesson .
Yes . That image was inserted in the scene .
Now he pushes her hand away .
That motion ...
If it wasn 't directed by Kim , that would have looked comical .
He looks like he is giving up .
She looks so desperate and sad as she tries to hold his hand for the last time .
But he pushes her hand away like that .
He seems so heartless and cruel .
In the film , the image of hands symbolizes desire .
It does .
In that sense , the image is indicative of his desire .
She is holding onto his neck .
And later she clings onto his leg .
She says , " If I let you go now , I won 't be able to find you in heaven . "
From the maid 's point of view , it really is a heart-wrenching line .
- You see the shadow ... - Yes , the shadow .
On the ceiling .
You see the same scene in Hwa-nyuh of 82 .
I saw that film in a huge theater with only a handful of people ,
and there was the same scene in which the woman was
dragged down the stairs with her head banging
on every step of the stairs . In Hwa-nyuh of 82 , the house
is bigger , so the banging sounds echoed louder .
And because the technology for sound effects was better
than the time when The Housemaid was made , it sounded
more realistic , that banging sound on the stairs .
It looked more dangerous for Na Young-hee , who played the maid
in Hwa-nyuh of 82 , and it must have hurt her head when filming it .
Watching it , you can also feel the pain on your own head .
- The acting here is so well done ... - Right .
So you can feel the desperation in your bones from this scene .
The way this scene is structured , too .
- It is so detailed . - Right .
Exhausted from work , the wife has fallen asleep .
She has been obsessed
- with work . - She has been consumed by it .
It is not about making money , but it is much more than that .
- It has been an obsession . - It has .
It has been her only escape , a way for her to forget .
Many female characters in Kim 's movies suffer from
some kind of mental illness .
In Woman of Fire , the main female character suffers from epilepsy .
Right .
In Hwa-nyuh of 82 , the maid suffers from some mental breakdown .
- Is it from a sense of guilt in the film ? - I think so .
I can 't remember it clearly .
- You see again ... - You do ...
You see the sewing machine turning again .
We saw the machines turning in the fabric mill
- in the first scene of the film . - We did .
It is a scene that matches that first scene .
You can see so clearly how this film was meticulously
conceived , planned , and filmed from the beginning .
When there are two characters in conversation , they always
stand in a position that shows their hierarchical relationship .
One is positioned physically higher than the other .
After The Housemaid was re-discovered in the late 90s and gained
international recognition , the film was restored in 2008 .
I was curious how international audiences would receive the film .
A couple of months ago , I had a chance to meet Director Martin Scorsese
and other people in the film industry . During the meeting ,
The Housemaid became one of the conversation topics , and
Director Scorsese said , " It 's a cinematic masterpiece . "
" You have to see it if you haven 't already . " " He said this in front of
Marion Cotillard , Paolo Sorrentino , and Fatih Akin , and
I felt so proud even though it wasn 't my film .
- I can see why you felt so proud . - I was very proud .
Scorsese also played an important role in restoring this film .
Right .
The man dies at the end , which is ...
- a very shocking conclusion . - It is .
- Usually , films have the mistress die at the end . - True .
The one who survives is the wife , with her tenacious instinct
- to survive . - Right .
- And in the remake ... - Here , you hear the sound of the baby crying .
- And you also hear ... - The sound of a train again .
Here is the problematic scene .
The audience now could burst out laughing at this scene ,
and I did , too , when I saw it for the first time .
When I watched it again and thought about why he did this ,
I was able to understand Kim 's reasons in a way .
Many people think that he had this ending due to the censorship at the time , which is not true .
I think it was done in consideration of the audience .
After watching so many horrendous things in the film ,
the audience probably would not have wanted to leave
the theater feeling so disturbed and troubled .
Doesn 't the maid look so cute and innocent there ?
When people watched the film in the theater , they must have
- laughed watching the ending . - I think so , too .
I 'm sure the ending scene was because of the director 's consideration of the audience .
The maid was the one who smoked behind the frame .
- Here it is different . - Right .
Dong-sik is the one who 's smoking .
And the film asks the audience to make sense of the ending .
Dong-sik says , " What would you have done ? "
" Would you have done differently ? "
It becomes almost inter - active at the end .
Dong-sik winks at the audience , and the film ends on a very sweet note .
The film is very cunning because Dong-sik is actually addressing
the men in the audience by asking , " What would you have done ? "
Women in the audience must have been quite familiar
with the situation of having a live-in maid in their house
because many middle-class people in the audience
had a live-in maid at the time .
So by throwing a question like " What would you have done ? "
Would not have made the audience feel at ease . It could have
had the adverse effect of making them feel very uncomfortable .
You mean the film ending wasn 't a moral lesson .
- It is only pretending to be one . - I see .
So this is the end of the film , and it is the time
for us to end our commentary for The Housemaid .
It 's been several years since I have watched the film ,
and I have to say I really enjoyed watching it again .
It is a great film .
I believe it is the dream of every director to make a film
like this one and make his or her contribution to film history .
I will try my best to make that happen .
Thank you for your commentary on the film today .
- Thank you . - Thank you .